Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse papers SSC.MS.00202
Sophia Smith Collection
- Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse personal and professional papers, 1951-1996; 1976-1996; 4; 8.437 linear feet (10 containers)
  - Audio recording "Cosmology and Creation - The Search for Meaning and Intelligibility", 1985 October 5; OP15a-OP15b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Science and Religion", 1985 October 18; OP16a-OP16b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Creation and Cosmology", 1985 October 19; OP17a-OP17b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "To the Dancer Belongs the Universe: Freedom and Bondage of Natural Law", 1986 October 17; OP18a-OP18b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Relationship Between Neuroscience and Psychoanalysis; Implications for Clinical Psychiatry", approximately 1974-1995; OP19; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Why Nuclear War?", approximately 1974-1995; OP20a-OP20b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Henderson Lecture", 1988 March 27; OP21; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Women in the Soviet Union", approximately 1974-1995; OP22; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Spirituality," "Hide and Seek of Prayer", approximately 1974-1995; OP23a-OP23d; 4 items (4 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Philadelphia Consortium", 1986 February 8; OP24; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Nuclear Colloquy at Trinity Church", 1982; OP25a-OP25c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Romancing the Bomb: Distortions of Love", approximately 1974-1995; OP26a-OP26b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Integrating Hypnotic Techniques and Jungian Approaches to Psychotherapy", 1987 February 25; OP27; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Beyond Violence -- The Protean Self," "Psychoanalytic Perspective on War", approximately 1974-1995; OP28a-OP28c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Jung's Interpretation of Neurosis I-III", approximately 1974-1995; OP30a-Op30f; 6 items (6 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Typology and Individuation I-II", approximately 1974-1995; OP31a-OP31d; 4 items (4 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Many-Sided Animus I-II", approximately 1974-1995; OP32a-OP32d; 4 items (4 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Five Sources of Evidence for Life After Death", 1991; OP33; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Survival or Super-Psi?", 1991; OP34; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Developing Strategies for Survival Research", 1991; OP35; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Advocacy Role of Religion in American Politics", 1991 April 22-23; OP36; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Rise of the New Religious Right in American Politics", 1991 April 22-23; OP37; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Future of Psychotherapy", 1991 January 15; OP38a-OP38b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Puer-Senex Polarity I-III", 1993 January; OP39a-OP39c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Persona I-II", 1993 January; OP40a-OP40b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Childhood Trauma I-III", 1993 January; OP41a-OP41c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Many-Sided Animus I-II", 1993 January; OP42a-OP42b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "The Shadow and the Overshadowed Self", 1993 January; OP43; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Sitting by the Well", 1993 November 12-14; OP44a-OP44b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Dream Interpretation I-III", 1994; OP45a-OP45c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Male Identity I-II", 1994; OP46a-OP46b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Meaning", 1991 October 27; OP47; 1 items (1 audiocassettes) (Box 10)
  - Audio recording "Chart Reading Priscilla Mueller", 1977 January 5; FP1; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Chart Reading Pris Mueller", 1977 February 17; FP2; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "RTB and Peggy Alden (psychic)", 1978 March 19; FP3; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Seth Session, Elmira, New York," "Jane Roberts, medium", 1972 June 12; FP4a-FP4b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Jane Roberts- Seth", 1973 June 12; FP5; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Uncle Toby", 1975 May 3; FP6a-FP6b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Bumpus", 1972 December; FP7; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Diya Channeling for Ruth Barnhouse", 1985 February 4; FP8; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "1) Prof Shilem on Kabbalah 2) Encounter with Frau Epper", approximately 1972; FP10; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "List of Whodun*ts -- to be stored in boxes in garage", approximately 1970-1980; FP11; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "For Nancy Hardesty - from RTB (this side only)", approximatley 1970-1980; FP12; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "RTB homily - Matt 23:23-26 + 2Thers2:1-17", 1974 August 27; S1; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "11th Annual Interfaith Service", 1985 February 2; S2; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "About Social Prejudice", 1986 June 15; S3; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Theological Education for the 80's", 1986 January 26; S4; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Perkins Xmas Serv", 1986 December; S5; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "You are what you think, not what you eat!", 1988 August 28; S6; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Lent and Sacrifice", 1991 March 3; S7; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "'Fully Human' - Really?", 1992 February 2; S8; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Lenten Series - 'Wednesday at St. Andrews'", 1990 March 7; S9; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Sermon at Good Shepard Church, Terrell, Tx.", 1990 July 29; S10; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Divorced Catholics", 1977 February; MF2; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Interview with Reverend Danny Martino on 'Homosexuality'", 1976 March 13; MF3; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Ruth Vassar Club: Men and Women", 1973 February 14; MF4; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Ethics of Man/Woman Relations", 1985 April 14; MF5; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Marriage and Family", 1984 September 17-1984 December 3; MF6a-MF6m; 13 items (13 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "RTB radio show - sex education", 1980 February 10; MF7; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Gay Rights", 1977 July 28; MF8; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Contemporary Spirituality for Men and Women", 1977; MF9a-MF9e; 5 items (5 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Human Identity", 1985 January 7-9; MF10a-MF10c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Marriage and Family", 1982 September 2-1982 December 2; MF11a-MF11i; 9 items (9 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Ethics of Man/Woman Relationships", approximately 1985; MF12a-MF12c; 9 items (9 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Christian Perspectives on Human Sexuality", 1985 September 13-1985 December 5; MF13a-MF13k; 11 items (11 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Women's Identity and the Church", approximately 1970-1980; MF14; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Marriage and Family", 1986 January 28-1986 April 29; MF15a-MF15j; 10 items (10 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "DMin-Marriage and Family", 1988 September 12-14; MF16a-MF16f; 6 items (6 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Human Sexuality", 1994 February 20; MF17; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Reconciliation of the Masculine and the Feminine", 1994 March 9; MF18; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "D. Min. Tape #1-Tape #8", 1987 March 16-18; SP7a-Sp7h; 8 items (8 audiocassettes) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Seth Session, Elmira NY," "Seth/Jane Roberts" use copies, 1972 June 12; FP4a-FP4b; 4 items (4 CDs) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Seth Session, Elmira NY," "Seth/Jane Roberts" preservation copies, 1972 June 12; FP4a-FP4b; 4 items (4 CDs) (Box 11)
  - Audio recording "Value of Life", 1980 May 2; P1a-P1b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Sociology of Sexual Disorders", approximately 1980; P2a-P2b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Q+A Smith College School of Social Work, 'Sexism in Counselling'", 1974 July 22; P3; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "The Native American: Psychological Consequences of American Colonialism at Home", 1987 December; P4a-P4b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Lynn Weiss Show: Mind/Body Connection", 1990 February 2; P5; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Panel on Psychoanalysis and Women: The Women's Movement, 20 Years Later; Its Effect on Treatment/Expperts [sic] Respond", approximately 1970-1985; P6a-P6b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Dr. Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse on KMGC Radio with Michelle Redmond", approximately 1974-1995; PW1; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Women's Global Peace- Keynote Speech", 1988 August 8; PW2-PW2b; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "The Christian Attitude to Nuclear War", 1984 January 17; PW3; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Results Radio: Ruth and Lynn, World Peace", 1989 July 23; PW4; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Sex and War", 1990 January 20; PW5; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Psych. of War Impulse", 1990 May 10; PW6; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Peacemakers' Celebration", 1989 August 27; PW7; 2 items (2 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "RTB: Peacemakers, Inc.", 1989 September 10; PW8; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Studies in Jung", 1985 January 28-1985 April 29; J1a-J1h; 8 items (8 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Jung Class", 1982 January 26-1982 March 3; J2a-J2e; 5 items (5 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Jung Seminar", 1982 September 2; J3; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Collective Shadow", approximately 1980-1990; J4; 1 items (1 audiocassette) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Studies in Jung", 1986 January 21-1986 April 25; J5a-J5l; 12 items (12 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Jung and Religion", 1986 November 8; J6a-J6c; 3 items (3 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
  - Audio recording "Freud and Jung- An Historical Perspective", approximately 1980-1990; J7a-J7d; 4 items (4 audiocassettes) (Box 12)
- Unreviewed accessions of Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse personal and professional materials, 1915-1999; 5; 21.5 linear feet (23 containers)
  This series consists of three unprocessed accessions of materials received from Ruth Barnhouse and her estate between 1999 and 2000.
  The materials relate to Barnhouse's personal life, as well as to her careers in psychotherapy and the ministry. All known materials related to Sylvia Plath have been removed from this series and added to Series 2 for ease of access.
  Materials from accession 1999-S-0014 that have been processed have been moved to Series 4. Note that box numbers repeat between accessions; boxes are being renumbered sequentially as they are processed.
  This series is open for use under the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections, except that it must be thoroughly reviewed by an archivist for confidential patient and ministerial information prior to access.
  This series is being processed on demand; please contact Smith College Special Collections to request that a portion be processed for your use.
  - Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse personal and professional materials, 1915-1999; 1999-S-0014; 19 linear feet (18 boxes)
    - Family materials, 1960-1996; 1999-S-0014 (Box 5)
    - Business papers, 1984-1994; 1999-S-0014 (Box 6)
    - Divorce, domestic arrangements and miscellaneous personal material, 1915-1994; 1999-S-0014 (Box 7)
    - Marriage and divorce, 1941-1947; 1999-S-0014 (Box 8)
    - Birthday celebration, 1988; 1999-S-0014 (Box 8)
    - Vassar 50th reunion, 1994; 1999-S-0014 (Box 8)
    - Material related to parents, 1941-1960; 1999-S-0014 (Box 8)
    - Poetry, Undated; 1999-S-0014 (Box 8)
    - Spirituality, mysticism, rituals, Undated; 1999-S-0014 (Box 8)
    - Research for book, "Sex and War", Undated; 1999-S-0014; Original accession form includes description under Box 8: "Box marked:"Research for book, Sex and War," with a PostIt which says: "sensative material, maverick theology, divorce, etc." (Box 8)
    - Speeches, sermons, conferences, 1974-1978; 1999-S-0014 (Box 9)
    - Materials related to ordination, 1972-1978; Undated; 1999-S-0014 (Box 9)
      Reports, evaluations on candidates for ordination is marked, "CONFIDENTIAL."
    - Speeches, sermons and articles, 1982-1995; 1999-S-0014 (Box 10)
    - Speeches, lectures, sermons with related correspondence, 1979-1983; 1999-S-0014 (Box 11)
    - Seminary papers, 1970-1976; 1999-S-0014 (Box 12)
    - Sermons, 1989-1993; 1999-S-0014 (Box 12)
    - Articles, pamphlets, miscellaneous printed materials, 1980-1999; 1999-S-0014 (Box 12)
    - Materials related to sexual identity and sexuality, 1970-1989; 1999-S-0014 (Box 12)
    - Youth seminary trip, 1985; 1999-S-0014 (Box 12)
    - Sermons, articles, book reviews by Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse with related articles, 1973-1996; 1999-S-0014 (Box 13)
    - Speeches, lectures, sermons conferences and miscellaneous materials, 1983-1985; 1999-S-0014 (Box 14)
    - Eranos, Assembly of World Religions and other conferences, 1960-1985; 1999-S-0014 (Box 15)
    - McLean Lecture Series, 1953-1955; 1999-S-0014 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, articles and papers related to myth, psychiatry and sexuality, 1978-1988; 1999-S-0014 (Box 15)
    - Materials related to Metropolitan State Hospital, 1956-1957; 1999-S-0014 (Box 15)
      This file marked "CONFIDENTIAL' in accession record
    - Miscellaneous files including related to McLean and Sibley hospitals, 1978-1996; 1999-S-0014 (Box 16)
    - Unsent letters by Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse, 1968-1975; 1999-S-0014 (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous materials including calendars, souvenirs, unused Christmas cards, 1947-1955; Undated; 1999-S-0014 (Box 17)
    - Card file research notes, 1960-1989; 1999-S-0014 (Box 19)
    - Materials related to ordination, 1978-1980; 1999-S-0014 (Box 19)
    - Family and other personal materials, photographs and slides, 1924-1999; 1999-S-0014 (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous materials and slides related to travel, 1964-1972; 1999-S-0014 (Box 21)
    - Audiovisual materials including video cassette tapes on nuclear war and reel-to-reel audio music tapes, Undated; 1999-S-0014 (Box 22)
    - Unidentified card file for library, Undated; 1999-S-0014 (Box 28)
  - Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse correspondence, writings, sermons, speeches, memorabilia, 1972-1999; 2000-S-0035; 2.5 linear feet (3 containers)
    - Diaries, calendar, work record, 1972-1996; 2000-S-0035 (Box 1)
    - The Typed Reporter, 1984-1996; 2000-S-35 (Box 2)
    - Sermons, 1976-1988; 2000-S-0035 (Box 2)
    - Public speaking notes, 1975-1994; 2000-S-0035 (Box 2)
    - The Dallas Summit, 1989; 2000-S-0035 (Box 2)
    - Calendars and work record, 1995-1996; 2000-S-0035 (Box 2)
    - Notes on scriptures and Paternayan yarn samples, Undated; 2000-S-0035 (Box 2)
    - Rituals, 1996; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - A.R.E. meditation course, 1980; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Overhead projector sheets, Undated; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Notes and speeches, 1990-1995; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Psychiatry, religion, science writings, 1980 May - 1989 December; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Perkins School of Theology book of tributes, 1989; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, greeting cards, 1998-1999; Undated; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - "Fundamentalism" article, 1996; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Sermons, Undated; 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
    - Memorabilia, 2000-S-0035 (Box 3)
  - Ruth Tiffany Barnhouse videotapes, 1934-1994; 2001-S-0021; 1.75 linear feet (2 boxes) (Box 1, Box 2)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.